<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="ReleaseNotesR2018a"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>GMAT R2018a Release Notes</title>

  <para>The General Mission Analysis Tool (GMAT) version R2018a was released
  March 2018. This is the first public release since June, 2017, and is the
  12th release for the project.</para>

  <para>Below is a summary of key changes in this release. Please see the full
  <link
  xlink:href="http://bugs.gmatcentral.org/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?version=11104&amp;styleName=Html&amp;projectId=10000&amp;Create=Create&amp;atl_token=B8F2-GAHA-O7AM-D5JZ%7C78ed3832b129ed9d51b5d382a7c04b0602d918d9%7Clin">R2018a
  Release Notes</link> on JIRA for a complete list.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Milestones and Accomplishments</title>

    <para>We're excited that GMAT has recently seen signficant adoption for
    operational misssion support.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT is now used as the primary system for maneuver planning and
        product generation for the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT is now used as the primary operational tool for orbit
        determination for the Solar and Heliospheric Observatory (SOHO)
        mission.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT is now used as the primary operational tool for maneuver
        planning, orbit determination, and product generation for the Advanced
        Composition Explorer (ACE) mission.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT is now used as the primary operational tool for maneuver
        planning, orbit determination, and product generation for the Wind
        mission.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In April 2018, the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS)
        mission is planned to launch. TESS has used GMAT as its primary tool
        for mission design and maneuver planning from proposal development
        through operations.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In April 2018, the LRO project will hold an operational
        readiness review to perform final evaluation of GMAT to replace GTDS
        as the primary operational orbit determination (OD) tool for the Lunar
        Reconnaissance Orbiter (LRO).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>New Features</title>

    <section>
      <title>Orbit Determination Enhancements</title>

      <para>The following new features and capabilities have been added to
      GMAT's estimation system.</para>

      <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>The batch estimator now supports a capability that freezes
            the measurements used for estimation after a user-specified number
            of iterations. This functionality avoids estimator chatter that
            can occur near solutions when some measurements are near the sigma
            edit boundary and are repeatedly removed during one iteration and
            then added back in the next iteration.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Numerics are improved when calculating Doppler and DSN_TCP
            measurement residuals, improving noise behavior in the
            residuals.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The GroundStation object supports a new troposphere model,
            the Marini model, matchig the implementation used in GTDS. One
            operational advantage of the Marini model is that it doesn’t
            require input of weather data at the Ground station. (Models that
            do accept weather data may have more accuracy.) <itemizedlist
                spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                  <para>Time is now modeled using three data members, a day
                  number, seconds of day, and fraction of second. High
                  precision time is surgically implemented in appropriate
                  models such as Earth rotation, planetary ephemerides and
                  others.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Range differences are computed using a Taylor series
                  and differenced Chebyshev polynomials.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Measurement simulation now accounts for central body
            occultation when orbiting bodies other than the Earth.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Estimation now supports solving for the Keplerian state
            estimation with a priori constraints.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>For BLS estimation, the user may choose to perform
            measurement editing using either the weighted root-mean-square
            (WRMS) of residuals, or the predicted weighted root-mean-square
            (WRMSP) of residuals. Residuals of elevation edited data are now
            reported.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The batch estimator report now shows the name of input files
            used in the configuration and the observation time span.
            Additionally, spacecraft hardware configurations and new
            measurement statistics information are included.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>GMD file improvements</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>As shown by the new features above, GMAT’s orbit determination
      (OD) capability has been significantly enhanced. As with all new
      releases, missions that use GMAT’s OD capability should perform a
      baseline set of regression/performance tests prior to using the new
      version of GMAT OD for operational purposes.</para>

      <para>Example scripts:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>See <filename>Ex_R2018a_CompareEphemeris.script</filename>
            for a new example on performing ephemeris compares at non-Earth
            bodies.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>See <filename>Ex_R2018a_MergeEphemeris.script</filename> for
            an example demonstrating merging ephemerides.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Built-in Optimizer</title>

      <para>GMAT now contains a built-in optimizer called Yukon, developed by
      the GMAT team. The algorithm uses an SQP line search algorithm with an
      active set QP-subproblem algorithm. Yukon is designed for small scale
      problems and is not applicable to large, sparse optimization problems.
      See the <link linkend="Yukon">Yukon</link> reference for more
      information.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Improvements</title>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Tide modeling is improved, and GMAT now supports lunar
        tides.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>STM propagation now includes variational terms from drag
        models.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The degree and order of STM contributions from harmonic gravity
        is now settable by the user and defaults to the maximum order on the
        gravity file or 100, whichever is lower.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The buffer size that determines the number of plot points stored
        by the OrbitView Resource is now exposed to the user.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Significant performance improvements have been made in the
        IRI2007 ionosphere model.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The script editor highlights errors and warnings found on the
        first pass of parsing.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT now supports body fixed and TOD coordinate systems for Code
        500 Ephemerides and supports all central bodies in the Code 500
        Ephemeris format.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The CommandEcho command has been added to GMAT to support
        printing commands to the message window and log file as they are
        executed in a mission sequence. This command is particularly useful
        when debugging user scripts. See the <link
        linkend="CommandEcho">CommandEcho</link> reference for more
        information.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Code500 propagator type now automatically detects the
        endianness when reading Code500 files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The STK ephemeris propagator now uses Hermite interpolation, and
        includes velocity information in the position interpolation for
        segments that contain fewer than 7 rows of data. Velocity
        interpolation for segments with fewer than 7 rows of data is performed
        by forming the hermite interpolating polynomial for position, and then
        differentiating the position interpolating polynomial to obtain the
        velocity.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can now set the step size of an ephemeris propagator during
        mission execution (i.e. after the BeginMissionSequence
        command).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The startup file now allows optional updating of the user
        configuration file. This avoids issues encountered when simultaneous
        instances of GMAT try to write to the user config file at the same
        time, resulting in a system error.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Python data file utility now updates data files used by the
        IRI2007 model.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The GMAT CMake based build system now supports plugin components
        developed by external groups.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT now supports GUI plugin components.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Compatibility Changes</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Batch estimation now requires the use of fixed step
        integration.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The RotationDataSource on CelestialBody Resources is deprecated
        and no longer has an effect.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Spacecraft EstimationStateType parameter is
        deprecated.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The EphemerisFile OutputFormat options ‘UNIX’ and ‘PC’ are
        deprecated. ‘BigEndian’ and ‘LittleEndian’ should be used
        instead.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The EarthTideModel on the ForceModel Resource has been renamed
        to TideModel</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GMAT now returns error codes via the command line interface to
        indicate if issues were encountered during system execution.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>When using the Write command to write Resource properties to a
        ReportFile, only scalar, real quantities are written. Properties that
        are either not real or are arrays are ignored and a warning is
        issued.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Upcoming Changes in R2019a</title>

    <para>This is the last version of GMAT tested on Windows 7.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Known &amp; Fixed Issues</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Issues</title>

      <para>Over 112 bugs were closed in this release. See the <link
      xlink:href="http://bugs.gmatcentral.org/issues/?filter=14102">"Critical
      Issues Fixed in R2018a" report</link> for a list of critical bugs and
      resolutions in R2018a. See the <link
      xlink:href="http://bugs.gmatcentral.org/issues/?filter=14103">"Minor
      Issues Fixed for R2018a" report</link> for minor issues addressed in
      R2018a.</para>

      <para><itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>The STK ephemeris propagator now correctly handles segments
            with fewer than 5 rows of data.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>STK ephemeris files that contain event boundaries now
            correctly count the number of ephemeris rows represented in the
            NumberOfEphemerisPoints keyword value pair.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Comments describing the source of ephemeris discontinuities
            in CCSDS ephemeris files are now written inside of meta data
            blocks.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Known Issues</title>

      <para>See the <link
      xlink:href="http://bugs.gmatcentral.org/issues/?filter=14104">"All Known
      Issues for R2018a" report</link> for a list of all known issues in
      R2018a.</para>

      <para>There are several known issues in this release that we consider to
      be significant:<informaltable frame="topbot">
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="0.2*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">ID</entry>

                <entry align="left">Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>GMT-5417</entry>

                <entry>Adaptive step size control behaves inconsistently when
                used in GMAT's navigation system. Fixed step integration is
                currently required for simulation and estimation.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>GMT-6202</entry>

                <entry>Spikes of up to 1 mm/sec may be observed in some cases
                in DSN_TCP and Doppler ionospheric corrections. The IRI2007
                model has some jumps in the electron density when moving
                through time. Spikes are caused when the start and end signal
                paths are located on different sides of these jumps.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>GMT-6367</entry>

                <entry>For Macs with a Touch Bar (GUI issue only): there
                appears to be an issue with WxWidgets, the third party GUI
                library used by GMAT, and the Mac Touch Bar. Crashes occur
                frequently and the traceback indicates that the issue lies in
                Apple code, related to the Touch bar specifically, possibly
                caused by a NULL string pointer. Our analysis suggests this
                issue cannot be addressed by the GMAT team or by WxWidgets;
                however, we will continue to investigate. In the meantime, the
                GMAT Console version will continue to work, and the GUI
                version (Beta) will work on Macs without a Touch Bar.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
